בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
Today's דף daf is דף פ, Daf Pei, 80. We pick up
at the משנה Mishna at the bottom of עין ט עמוד ב.
Ayin Tes Amud Beis.
And we move to a slightly different topic. I mean, again, it's
interesting how this פרק perek of course has mostly been devoted to
נאמנות, ne'emanus, יסוד יוחסין, yesod yuchsin, but going a little back and
forth between some classic, what I would call קידושין kiddushin topics. So
the most proximate משנה Mishna was about somebody who gives a שליח
shaliach to מארס me-oreis his daughter, and then the question is whose
קידושין kiddushin took place first, his or his שליח'ס, shaliach's, or if
she did it, hers or her שליח'ס. shaliach's. Now, we get back
to like, I would say, a theme from two משניות Mishnayos ago,
which is somebody who testifies that his child is a ממזר, mamzer,
and is he believed or not, and here we get to somebody
else testifying about his family and whether or not he's believed. So
let's take a look at this משנה. Mishna. I had a question
from yesterday also, so is there any element of self-incrimination in all
of these questions about whether somebody can testify about? Some of them
could be. I mean, the fact that a child is a ממזר
mamzer is more incriminating your wife than incriminating yourself.
But that doesn't seem to be the primary concern. Actually, in some
of those cases where you're not allowed to self-incriminate,
your testimony is not taken to
convict yourself, but it is sometimes split, the principle of פלגינן דיבורא,
palginan dibura, and we actually can take the element of your testimony
that affects other people. So the issue here of dismissing it is
not because of self-incrimination, it's just that it's not sufficient testimony. So
let's take a look at the משנה. Mishna. מי שיצא הוא ואשתו
למדינת הים, Mi she-yatzah hu ve-ishto li-medinas ha-yam, a man and his
wife went to a faraway, you know, to a faraway place. ובא
הוא ואשתו ובניו, U-va hu ve-ishto u-vanav, and then he came back
after many years with his wife and many children. ואמר אשה שיצאת
עמי למדינת הים הרי היא זו, Ve-amar ishah she-yatzta imi li-medinas ha-yam
harey hi zo, this woman is the wife I left with, you
know, maybe it's 20 years later, people don't recognize her, right? But
this is the wife that I left with. ואלו בניה, Ve-elu baneha,
and these are the children that she gave birth to over in
מדינת הים. medinas ha-yam. אינו צריך להביא ראיה לא על האשה ולא
על הבנים, Eino tzarich le-havi rayah lo al ha-ishah ve-lo al ha-banim,
he does not have to prove any, bring any evidence about his
wife. Now רש״י Rashi says this means he doesn't have to prove
that she is of good יחוס yichus because presumably that was established
here when he married her. And presumably also what part of the
חידוש chiddush is that even if maybe we don't fully recognize her,
he is believed since he left with a wife and came back
with a wife, he's believed to say it's the same woman. But
also he doesn't have to bring any proof that these are her
children. And since she was known to have had acceptable יחוס, yichus,
the children also have acceptable יחוס. yichus. So the גמרא Gemara is
going to discuss why exactly he believed to say that these are
her children. The גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say that the children basically
are sort of still young and are cleaving to her, כרוך אחריה,
koruch achareha, literally wrapped around her. So it's clear that she's you
know mothering to the children and therefore the presumption is that they
are hers, which is an interesting fact because one could imagine other
potential possible scenarios. What about adult children? Don't adult children also have
behavior bonds?
That's true too. Maybe they're getting in fights.
Right, but that's a good point, that's a good point. Okay, now
לא על האשה ולא על הבנים. lo al ha-ishah ve-lo al ha-banim.
מתה, Meisah,
now let's say he says actually my wife died when we were
overseas. ואלו בניה, Ve-elu baneha, but these are the children she gave
birth to. מביא ראיה על הבנים ואינו מביא ראיה על האשה, Meivi
rayah al ha-banim ve-eino meivi rayah al ha-ishah, he has to bring
proof that these children are his wife's children. I don't know how
he would do it, some birth certificate, somebody would come and testify
that these are his wife's children. But then he does not have
to bring proof about his wife that his wife is מיוחס meyuchas
because that was presumed when he married her, when he left here.
So once he presumes that he can prove that these are his
wife's children, they are also understood to be מיוחס. meyuchas. אשה נשאתי
במדינת
הים, Ishah nasasi bi-medinas ha-yam,
now let's say he comes back, he left single, and he comes
back and he says I got married
over where I was in this faraway country. והרי היא זו ואלו
בניה, Ve-harey hi zo ve-elu baneha, and this is the woman I
married and these are her children. מביא ראיה על האשה ואינו מביא
ראיה על הבנים, Meivi rayah al ha-ishah ve-eino meivi rayah al ha-banim,
so the children are presumed to be the woman's. Again, in some
similar scenario where they're acting in a way that shows that they
treat her as the mother. So that we can presume that they
are her children. But we don't know her יחוס. yichus. And we
don't know, you know, maybe he's a כהן Kohen and she's a
גרושה gerushah or whatever, some type of a יחוס yichus question. So
therefore if we want to establish that the kids are of good
יחוס yichus or that they're not חללים, chalalim, any type of normal
sort of determination we would have to make when somebody's marrying a
woman, we would still have to now go ahead and address that
situation and bring proof about her יחוס. yichus. Now let's say he
says מתה ואלו בניה, meisah ve-elu baneha,
I married a woman when I was in a faraway country and
these are her children. Okay, in that case there's no
behavior. wants that status to be presumed to apply to the children,
he has to bring a proof that the children are also that
woman's children. Okay, so basically if she's here with the woman and
the children and the children are acting in a particular way, then
that creates a presumption that they're her children. All right, if the
children aren't here, then he has to prove that they're her children.
If he got married to the woman over here, then we knew
her יחוס yichus in terms of יחוס yichus issues. Okay, for her
similarly, if she got married here, then we knew her יחוס. yichus.
If he got married overseas, we don't know her יחוס yichus and
he would have to prove her יחוס. yichus. So the presence of
the children with the mother creates a presumption that they're her children.
When they're not together with the mother, they have to be proven
to be her children. And the fact that he got married to
this woman here, then we know the יחוס. yichus. If he got
married to the woman overseas, we don't know the יחוס yichus and
that would have to be proven. Okay, so the one thing that
really has to be addressed here is how do we presume that
these are her children. So that's what the גמרא Gemara focuses on.
אמר רבה בר רב הונא וכולן דכרוכין אחריה. Amar Rabah bar Rav
Huna, v'kulan d'kruchin achareha. All these cases where she's with the children
and we presume they're her children is when they are literally like
intertwined with her, wrapped around her. Okay, so basically it's clear that
the way they relate to her is as a mother. That creates
that presumption. Does his claim play any role here or if he
dies and they all... Oh, that's an interesting point. And people recognize
the woman? Right, but let's say I mean even they don't. The
woman just says 'I was married to this man' and
particularly regarding the children because the presumption apparently is supported or created
by the behavior. Right, that's a good point. So maybe their behavior
itself creates that presumption that she's the mother. Interesting question, but if
she's dead,
maybe we can presume that those are her children but how would
we know who the father is? You know, right? But you're right,
presumably that behavior of כרוכין אחריה kruchin achareha suffices. You know, I
mean or it shouldn't require his claim, presumably any claim with that
behavior, whether his or her. But that's a good question. Or perhaps
with his claim, the bar for the behavior is lower. Right, that's
the question. What if it were her claim? Meaning just observed behavior
without any framing presumably would not be as significant, right? But if
it were her claim 'these are my kids' and they're acting in
a particular way... Is it the fact that it's his claim that
gives it more weight than hers? Yeah, I don't know. It's a
good question. I don't know. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: אשה נשאתי במדינת הים. Ishah nasati
b'medinat hayam. So I married a woman. מביא ראיה על האשה ואין
צריך להביא ראיה על הבנים. Mavi re'ayah al ha'ishah v'ein tzarich l'havi
re'ayah al habanim. So he has to prove the woman's status because
we don't know, you know, he just married this woman, we don't
know anything about her. But if he's here with her and small
kids, we don't have to prove anything about the kids. ומביא ראיה
על הגדולים ואין צריך להביא ראיה על הקטנים. Umavi re'ayah al hagedolim
v'ein tzarich l'havi re'ayah al haketanim.
Now, even if he's here with kids, if the kids are גדול...
gadol... again I don't know how big is adult, but adult in
a way that their behavior would not make it so obvious that
they are, you know, being that she's their mother. You know, maybe
she's their stepmother, who knows, just because they get into a fight
with her doesn't prove one way or the other, right?
So anyway, the more evidence of their behavior is when they are
small children. Of course the interesting question is if they're adults why
don't you just ask them, right? So that gets similar to Joe's
question. What? How do they know who their mother is?
Yeah, but I guess if they could say for the past ten
years she's been acting as our mother and they testify to behavior
that had we observed it as minors we would that would have
been the behavior of כרוכין אחריה. kruchin achareha. You know, I don't
know, it is a good question. You know, but anyway, but if
so this is similar to this idea of כרוכין אחריה. kruchin achareha.
Only small children that are really clearly being mothered by her are
the ones we presume are hers.
במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, when is this true? באשה אחת.
B'ishah achat. If he basically comes back with one woman or he
makes a claim about one woman. אבל בשתי נשים, Aval bishtei nashim,
let's say he basically says 'I married two women in מדינת הים'
medinat hayam or he left with two women and he came back
with one. Okay, in that case מביא ראיה על האשה ועל הבנים
על הגדולים ועל הקטנים. mavi re'ayah al ha'ishah v'al habanim, al hagedolim
v'al haketanim. The fact that there are these small children that are
wrapping themselves around this woman that he came back with and she's
mothering them is
is not sufficient because we could say that these are her stepchildren,
right? That he married two wives, one of them died, and of
course since she's the remaining wife and these are the children she's
going to take them over. Of course one does wonder whatever happened
about הפה שאסר. hapeh she'asar. He came back with one woman. He
could have said 'I only married one woman.' He says he married
two and these are the children of the woman that is still
alive, right?
Presumably he could be believed because he could have said it was
only one woman. You know, 'I only married one woman.' So I
don't know, maybe he doesn't have a הפה שאסר hapeh she'asar or
maybe we know that he left with two women.
Well right, that gets back also... Exactly. Yeah. Alright. So אמר ריש
לקיש. Amar Resh Lakish. So now
we're going to focus in and what level standard of proof is
this issue that the children are כרוכה אחריה, kerucha achareha, are intertwined
with her, wrapped around her? How much of that we can really
fully presume that they are her children? So אמר ריש לקיש, Amar
Resh Lakish, לא שנו אלא
בקדשי הגבול. lo shanu ela be-kodshei ha-gvul. That's only what comes to
sanctified things outside the בית המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash, in the in the
borders, meaning not in the temple precinct, meaning תרומה. terumah. So if
he was a כהן, Kohen, then we will presume that these are
her children and his children and that they're מיוחס meyuchas and all
of that to allow them to eat תרומה. terumah. אבל ליוחסין לא.
Aval le-yuchasin lo.
But when it comes to question about can we now assume that
let's say his children from this woman is or are daughters, and
can he marry this daughter off to a כהן? Kohen? Remember we
have been discussing until now a higher standard of evidence and research,
that you would go back four generations of mothers, if you remember
that, in order to marry a woman off to a כהן. Kohen.
So here if all we have is the presumption of their behavior,
that might be enough to eat תרומה, terumah, but that's not enough
to prove that they're her children for יוחסין yuchasin purposes, for whom
now that they can marry. ורבי יוחנן אמר, Ve-Rabbi Yochanan amar, and
Rabbi Yochanan says, אפילו ליוחסין. afilu le-yuchasin. No,
even for יוחסין yuchasin purposes we would, you know,
this behavior is evidence enough that they really are her children and
that works even for this higher standard of יוחסין. yuchasin. ואזל רבי
יוחנן לטעמיה. Ve-azal Rabbi Yochanan le-ta'ameih. Now we know Rabbi Yochanan goes
according to his reasoning because as we're going to see, Rabbi Yochanan
accepts, you know, what we're going to call a חזקה, chazakah, a
presumption of facts based on observed behavior, we're going to accept that
as a very high standard of proof and even for very, very
weighty issues and יוחסין yuchasin would be included. Where do we see
that? דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, De-amar Rabbi Chiyya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba says in the
name of Rabbi Yochanan, מלקין על החזקות. malkin al ha-chazakos. You would
give lashes based on a חזקה, chazakah,
וסוקלין ושורפין על החזקות, ve-soklin ve-sorfin al ha-chazakos, and you would actually
give, you know, the capital punishment, you would stone somebody or burn
somebody because of a presumption, ואין שורפין תרומה על החזקה. ve-ein sorfin
terumah al ha-chazakah. But you would not, the one thing, you could
burn a human being, you gotta love this context, שורפין, sorfin, but
you wouldn't burn תרומה terumah if there was a חזקה chazakah that
the תרומה terumah became טמא, tamei, you wouldn't burn it based on
a חזקה. chazakah. Now that seems completely bizarre. So let's first, before
we get to the תרומה terumah case, let's first worry about the
first two cases. Okay. מלקין על החזקות, malkin al ha-chazakos, what would
be the case you would give lashes based on a presumption? Now
I want to say something about the word חזקה. chazakah.
חזקה chazakah sometimes means, well חזקה chazakah can mean something in בבא
בתרא, Bava Basra, which we're not even going to get into, but
חזקה chazakah can sometimes mean status quo, like, you know, somebody had
a status quo like we had it the other day about being
a נערה, na'arah, when did she become a בוגרת, bogeres, so we'll
assume that she hasn't become a בוגרת, bogeres, or if we see
that she became a בוגרת bogeres we'll assume it came at a
later time rather than an earlier time because her status quo before
that had been a נערה. na'arah. The מקוה mikvah had a חזקה
chazakah of having a full amount of water in it, we don't
know when it lost the water, so right, maybe we're going to
assume the חזקה chazakah presumes that it happened later rather than earlier,
or this vessel had a חזקה chazakah of being טמא, tamei, we
dunked it in a מקוה, mikvah, we don't know if the מקוה
mikvah was כשר, kasher, we'll assume it retained its חזקה. chazakah. That's
a status quo. There's a different type of way the word חזקה
chazakah is used, which is a presumption of facts based on observed
behavior. So for example, חזקה אין אשה מעיזה פניה בפני בעלה. chazakah
ein ishah me-izah paneiha bifnei ba'alah. If a woman claims to her
husband, you divorced me, we take that as a good evidence that
she was divorced because there's a חזקה chazakah that she would not
be brazen enough to say that to her husband if she was
lying. Okay, so based on certain presumptions we have about how people
act, we can infer,
presume, certain realities, certain, you know, so here the חזקה chazakah is,
kids who are wrapped around this woman that this guy is coming
back with, presumably she's their mother, okay, that's the חזקה. chazakah. Okay,
so that's to what he is saying is when we can establish
certain facts based on presumptions of behavior, okay, that can give us
so much of a sense that that are the facts in question
that we would actually, you know, give מלקות malkus and the death
penalty as a basis of it. So let's take a look at
what those examples are.
Okay. מלקין על החזקות, malkin al ha-chazakos, כרב יהודה, ke-Rav Yehuda, like
רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. דאמר רב יהודה, De-amar Rav Yehuda, הוחזקה נדה
בשכנותיה. huchzekah niddah bi-shchenoteiha. If a woman has been established amongst her
neighbors as being a נדה, niddah, she wears certain garments that she
would only wear when she's a נדה, niddah, you know, she said
certain things to her friends, okay, and now that there's this presumption
among her, like, friends, her circle of friends, oh yeah, she's a
נדה niddah now so she'll be going to the מקוה mikvah in
a few days, and that's the presumption that has arisen based on
things she's been saying and ways she's been acting.
In that case בעלה לוקה עליה משום נדה. ba'alah lokeh aleiha mishum
niddah. If we saw that the husband had sex with her during
this time, we would give him lashes. lashes, and I wish we'd
give her lashes too, because of transgressing the prohibition of having sex
when the woman is a נידה. niddah. Even though there's no evidence,
right? Nobody checked her בדיקה bedikah cloth or whatever, or looked at
her underwear or you know or clothes or her sheets, but just
the fact that this is a presumption now that's arisen by ways
she's been acting, that establishes it as a matter of fact. Now,
similarly, סוקלין
ושרפין על החזקות, soklin vesorfin al hachazakot, you would give stoning and
burning, execute somebody based on a חזקה. chazakah. דרבה בר אבונה, Derabbah
bar Avuna, דאמר רבה בר אבונה, de'amar Rabbah bar Avuna, איש ואישה
תינוק ותינוקת ish ve'isha tinok vetinoket
שגדלו בתוך הבית, shegidelu betoch habayit, let's say a man and a
woman or with a young boy and a young girl and they
all grow up in the same house. Nobody was at their wedding,
nobody saw a marriage certificate, nobody was at the hospital when she
was giving birth. Everybody just looks at them and presumes that they're
all a family, okay? In that case, נסקלין זה על זה ונשרפין
זה על זה. niskaalin zeh al zeh venisrafin zeh al zeh. If
basically the young you know the the presumed father has sex with
the presumed daughter or the presumed son with the presumed mother, all
these types of cases, you would all you know we'd consider it
incest and we'd give them the death penalty for that, even though
there's no evidence that anybody is related. It's just the presumption we
have that they're living together as a family. Now, yeah, this is
a big deal, right? But we can assume certain presumed facts, you
know, take them into evidence, you know, because that is the way
in which this is perceived within the community. Now, I'll give you
somewhat of a per... First of all, the important point is that
this is not a standard of proof that the actual act was
performed. If you have a חזקה, chazakah, it's not the same as
saying, "Well, you know חזקה chazakah that this was the guy that
he murdered this guy so we'll go ahead and kill him." No,
no, no, you know, the evidence of proof that the act, the
transgression was performed, that needs to be two witnesses. The גמרא Gemara
even gives a case of somebody running after somebody with a knife,
like you know saying he's going to kill him, and they run
into a barn and you know you the witnesses come in two
seconds later and they see the guy on the floor with stab
wounds who's like mortally wounded, the other person with a knife over
him with blood dripping from the knife, and you can't go ahead...
that's not sufficient evidence that he's the murderer because nobody actually witnessed
the murder. Okay? So that actually is the the act of the
of the crime had to be, the sin, had to be directly
witnessed. It's the presumption of facts around, you know, that were already
established ahead of time: who's the father, who's the son, this woman's
a נידה, niddah, who's this, who's that. There, right, we don't have
to get like birth certificates and somebody to testify in the hospital
that this was the mother. As long as there's a sort of
it's established within the community these presumptions, that is assumed to be
like that assumes that those things are fact, which is very strange
because at the end of the day, you're still going to murder
them based on something you don't know for sure. Right, which you
know and for any any case, wouldn't you have to prove that
the person was Jewish
so then you'd just have to
assume? Right, right, exactly. So yeah, it's a very good point. I
mean, you know, one imagines like it'd be impossible to run society
if you had to prove every fact in evidence and that's part
of this issue. A similar case is the issue of עד אחד.
ed echad. We say עד אחד נאמן באיסורין. ed echad ne'eman be'issurin.
So the so רמב"ם Rambam says let's say one witness testifies this
piece of meat in front of you is חלב. chelev. And then,
so we would assume it's חלב chelev forbidden fat. And then somebody
comes to eat it and witness says, "Don't eat it, it's חלב,"
chelev, and he says, "I don't care," and he eats it anyway.
We'd give that person lashes, even though the presumption of the status
of the meat was only through one witness. Right, if the act
had been done only with one witness, we wouldn't give him lashes.
But we can establish that. Now רמב"ם Rambam actually says that idea
of עד אחד נאמן באיסורין ed echad ne'eman be'issurin and then we
would actually the court would prosecute based on that if an act
occurred later. רמב"ם Rambam says that's only for מלקות, malkut, not for
מיתה. mitah. So I'm trying to think about what a case might
be about a מיתה mitah case, but I don't know what would
be a case of מיתה mitah that would presume about a particular
status of an object. Maybe something relating to שבת, Shabbat, I'd have
to think about it. Anyway, but anyway, but the רמב"ם Rambam says
that would only be for a מלקות malkut case, not for מיתה
mitah case. Here we're saying it even for a capital punishment because
here it's not just one witness says it and we believe one
person, but we didn't presume it already. Here we're dealing with cases
with as a society we have certain presumptions about the facts, you
know, and that creates and that makes them considered to be fact
for purposes for all other הלכות, halachot, okay, even for הלכות halachot
that will translate into the death penalty. All right. It's like in
secular law, if you ever read a what do they call it
when you when you file a lawsuit? Yeah.
So there's this whole preamble just pages and pages and pages about,
you know, establishing the jurisdiction. all those things that you know are
pretty much I mean they're all standard. Right, right, right. But if
it's not part of the document then some then it could be
challenged. I see. Interesting, interesting. Yeah, when I was on a grand
jury one thing we had to do was to establish that the
crime was committed in the Southern District of New York. Right, right.
Even though it seemed obvious we had to actually make that you
have to assume the jurisdiction. Yeah. Right. Okay. So that because we
will establish it so much as a proof for issues like of
the death penalty, the point is presumably it'll be good enough for
יוחסין yichsun as well. Okay. Now all that makes a lot of
sense, but the question is then why can't we burn תרומה Terumah
as rest of סוטה Sotah does? So let's take a look. Okay.
But first we're going to have a story. אמר רבי שמעון בן
פזי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא, Amar Rabbi Shimon
ben Pazi amar Rabbi Joshua ben Levi mishum Bar Kappara, מעשה באשה
שבאה לירושלים, maaseh be-isha she-ba'ah l'Yerushalayim, a woman came to Jerusalem, ותינוק
מורכב לה על כתפיה, v'tinok murkav lah al ktefeha, and she had
an infant on her shoulders. Oh, actually here you see Dov, here's
a case where the husband isn't testifying and presumably it sounds like
the mother isn't testifying, right?
והגדילתו, ve-higdilto, and she raised him, and then after he became an
adult or whatever, after you know, בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, ובא עליה,
u-ba aleha, they had sex with one another. והביאום לבית דין וסקלוהם,
v'hivium l'beit din v'saklum, and both of them were brought to court
and they were both executed. Okay, it was a mother and a
son having sex. לא מפני שבנה ודאי, lo mipnei she-binah vaddi, not
that we had any evidence that this was her son, אלא מפני
שכרוך אחריה, ela mipnei she-korekh achareiha, there's the phrase of כרוך אחריה.
korekh achareiha. Okay, because he was like, you know, she was raising
him and she was, you know, and therefore there's a presumption that
she was the son. So there's a good case; she's not claiming
anything, the husband isn't claiming anything, right? I mean, but because that
presumption gets created, that becomes then accepted as evidence. Did you want
to say something? כרוך אחריה korekh achareiha is a little ironic. I
know, כרוך אחריה korekh achareiha like right, intertwined with her, right. One
does wonder about that. This could be a problem for Woody Allen.
Good point. I mean it does raise the fact that there are
realities of stepchildren and other types of children. And again, maybe if
somebody actually said that at the outset, by the way you should
know this is my stepson, it would never have developed into a
חזקה. chazakah. You know, but if you don't say anything and you
act in a certain way and everybody, you know, it develops these
presumptions around that, right? I mean there's like, I'm thinking about something
like you know that TV show The Americans or there's the other
show about like a family moves into a place but they're really
all like, you know, spies or whatever they're just faking it, not
really a family or something. Anyway, but so if you say something
the חזקה chazakah never develops, but if you don't say anything and
you act in a certain way and that leads to certain presumptions
then that becomes accepted as fact. Okay, so then the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
So all that makes good sense and that would work for יוחסין.
yichsun. But how about this thing about תרומה? Terumah?
Okay, ואין שורפין תרומה על חזקות, ve-ein sorfin Terumah al chazakot, דאמר
ריש לקיש שורפין על החזקות, d'amar Reish Lakish sorfin al ha-chazakot, you
would burn תרומה Terumah
meaning that there's a presumption it became טמא, tamei, you would now
burn it, even if you don't know for certain that it became
טמא. tamei. רבי יוחנן אמר אין שורפין, Rabbi Yochanan amar ein sorfin,
you do not. ואזדו לטעמייהו, v'azdu l'ta'amayhu, they go according to their
reasonings. דתנן תינוק שנמצא בצד העיסה ובצק בידו, d'tnan tinok she-nimtza b'tzad
ha-issah v'batzek b'yado, you have an infant that's by some dough and
you know by dough that and he has a little piece of
dough in his hand. So I'm going to read this תוספות's Tosafot
way. תוספות's Tosafot way is the presumption here, the thing we don't
know for a fact, is that he touched the dough because maybe
some adult came and gave him a little piece of the dough.
Okay, we don't know exactly, but we presume that the infant took
the piece of dough himself from the larger, you know, amount of
dough. The question is the larger dough, not the dough in the
infant's hands, but the larger dough that you're about to bake into
חלה Challah or doughnuts or whatever you're going to make out of
it, has that become טמא tamei or not? Did the infant touch
it? You see that he has a little piece in his hand.
Yeah, so the infant is טמא? tamei? Yeah, so we're going to
so that's going to be also רש"י Rashi says we know he
touched the dough, the presumption is that he's טמא. tamei. תוספות Tosafot
says we know he's טמא, tamei, the presumption that we don't know,
you know, but that we're presuming is that he touched the dough.
Okay, the reason תוספות Tosafot says we know he became טמא tamei
is apparently because he's been being held by his mother, his mother
just gave birth so though again I don't know if he had
dough he presumably he can't really be just an infant. But anyway
there's some you know we assume the mother is טמא, tamei, she's
a נדה niddah or she just gave birth and she's been holding
him and nursing him, so that's how תוספות Tosafot says we actually
know he's טמא. tamei. רש"י Rashi says no we just presume he's
טמא, tamei, we know he touched the dough. But one of these
things is presumed to be known, the other is to be is
presumed. Okay, one of these is known, one is presumed. רבי מאיר
מטהר, Rabbi Meir metaher, Rabbi Meir says
the dough is טהור. tahor. וחכמים מטמאין, ve-Chachamim metamin, and the חכמים
Chachamim say it's טמא. tamei.
מפני שדרכו של תינוק לטפח. mipnei she-darko shel tinok l'tape'ach. Why the
חכמים Chachamim say that it's טמא? tamei? Because an infant will normally
you know like touch things. Like the word טפח tefach is a
handbreadth. You know he'll like pat on things, he'll touch anything in
his way. And therefore if he has the dough in his hand,
presumably he touched the dough, I'm going to read it תוספות's Tosafot
way. Okay, רש"י Rashi says it means לטפח l'tape'ach means he probably
goes around and he fools around in the in the dung heap
and touched some טמא. tamei. or character or something. Okay. ואבינן בה,
Ve-avinan ba, מאי טעמא mai ta'ama דרבי מאיר? de-Rabbi Meir? So what's
the reason for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says that we presume the dough is
טהור? tahor? קסבר kasavar רוב תינוקות מטפחין, rov tinokot metapchin, it's true.
The majority of infants pat around, ומיעוט אין מטפחין, u-miut ein metapchin,
but there are some that don't, ואיכא חזקת טהרה, ve-ika chezkat tahara,
and the dough has a חזקה chazaka of being טהור. tahor. וסמוך
מיעוטא לחזקה, u-smoch miuta le-chazaka, so you take the minority possibility that
the תינוק tinok did not touch the dough and you add it
to the status—this is a different חזקה, chazaka, this is the חזקה
chazaka status quo, not the חזקה chazaka of presumed
behavior—you add it to the status quo of the dough, ואיתרע ליה
רובא, ve-itrei lei rova, and that counteracts the רוב. rov. And because
it counteracts the רוב, rov, you now have like a ספק, safek,
and presumably we're dealing in a case of a רשות הרבים, reshus
ha-rabim, so a ספק טומאת טהור, safek tumas tahor, or even if
it's a רשות היחיד, reshus ha-yachid, we'll see in a minute. When
do we say that a ספק טומאת טמא safek tumas tamei in
רשות היחיד? reshus ha-yachid? That's only if there's somebody there who could
be asked, there's שיש בו דעת לישאל. she-yesh bo da'at lishael. But
if the infant is the only one there and he's not around
to be asked because he couldn't give us any information, so then
we say ספק טהור. safek tahor. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir makes
it a ספק safek and therefore it's טהור. tahor. But the חכמים
Chachamim say, no, it's like it we assume that it happened and
it's טמא, tamei, even in a רשות הרבים. reshus ha-rabim. Now, how
do you know you wouldn't burn it in that case? Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this,
רבנן, Rabbanan, and the Rabbis would say that, no, מיעוטא כמאן דליתא
דמי, miuta keman d'leita dami, the minority possibility is not given any
weight,
רובא וחזקה, Ruba ve-chazaka, and therefore we go by the majority, majority
the kids touch and thing, they touch the dough, רובא וחזקה, Ruba
ve-chazaka, so it's the רוב rov that he touched the dough against
the חזקה chazaka of the status quo of the dough, ורובא עדיף,
ve-rova adif, and רוב rov trumps חזקה. chazaka. Now, how do we
know that you would not burn the dough according to רבי יוחנן?
Rabbi Yochanan? Because that's what this is coming to prove. That even
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who goes by חזקות chazakot of presumptions would
not burn the dough. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, by the
way, before we get to that I should say, that רש"י Rashi
already connects this to רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir general position that חיישינן
למיעוטא. chashinan le-miuta. We know in general that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says if there's a minority possibility about something, we have to be
concerned about it, we can't just act and presume everything goes by
the majority. There's also a real minority possibility and therefore we can't
ignore it. So that here as well, he gives weight to the
מיעוט miut and therefore you add that with the חזקה, chazaka, the
status quo of the dough, and you presume that the dough is
still טהור, tahor, or at least it's a ספק, safek, and if
it's a ספק, safek, ספק רשות הרבים טהור. safek reshus ha-rabim tahor.
Somebody told me the other day this idea that she knows somebody
who's like this, you know, whatever medical researcher, you know, and he
knows all the statistics of these, you know, diseases, like it's one
in a million, you know, one in a hundred million or whatever.
But anyway, this person came down with something that like, you know,
it was extremely rare. So this person said, when you're in the
numerator, it doesn't matter what the denominator is.
If you're the one in a million, it doesn't matter that the
denominator is a million. So that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
If there's a small possibility, we have to look at that possibility,
we can't ignore it. And here, therefore, it combines with the status
quo of the dough, and therefore it's, you know, it's a ספק
safek at least, and ספק ברשות הרבים טהור. safek bi-reshus ha-rabim tahor.
Whereas the חכמים Chachamim say you ignore that small possibility, you go
by רוב, rov, you presume the dough is טמא. tamei. Yes, exactly.
Are these formulas like generalized or pulled out anywhere? Like, oh, how
do we decide between a חזקה chazaka and a רוב rov or
this is...? Yes, yes. The first פרק perek of חולין Chullin is
a central discussion about this, about all these different presumptions of how
to deal with cases of
doubt: רוב, rov, חזקה, chazaka, קרוב, karov, מיעוט, miut, all those things,
מצוי ואינו מצוי. matzui ve-eino matzui. The first discussion, like right in
the beginning of חולין, Chullin, it basically asks that question: רובא וחזקה,
Ruba ve-chazaka, which is עדיף? adif? You know? So it has all
of those issues. I was joking once, I said I was going
to give a series of classes, a course called 'Living with Doubt'.
And it'll be about רוב rov and חזקה chazaka and ספק. safek.
Which is accurate. But if you think about it, it's true because
basically what these are saying is, a lot of life we don't
know the facts. We have to just navigate without knowing for certain
what the facts are, right? So that's what these are here to
do is to tell you how you have to go ahead and
make decisions even if you don't really know. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says, now, according to the חכמים Chachamim we're going to say
it's a presumption that he touched the dough. Are you going to
burn the dough?
אמר ריש לקיש משום רבי אושעיא, Amar Reish Lakish mishum Rabbi Oshaya,
זו היא ששורפין עליה את התרומה. zo hi she-sorfin aleha et ha-terumah.
You would burn תרומה. terumah. Now, this is ironic, because it was
the same ריש לקיש Reish Lakish from before that remember by the
case about who do you presume are the children, that would say
that would not be a good enough standard of proof for יוחסין.
yuchasin. For יוחסין yuchasin you need a higher standard of proof. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, no, חזקה chazaka is good enough, you would
kill a guy based on חזקה, chazaka, so it's good enough for
יוחסין. yuchasin. But here when it comes to the תרומה, terumah, they
reverse themselves. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says you would burn the תרומה
terumah based on this
presumption. Now, here now things are beginning to make sense. Because when
we initially presented it, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, if you have
a חזקה chazakah that's enough to go ahead and burn a person,
but not enough to burn תרומה. terumah. And I said that's crazy,
right? Obviously the standard of proof should be higher for executing somebody
than for burning תרומה. terumah. But here what it sounds like is
that he's really not saying you cannot have a חזקה chazakah that's
good enough to burn תרומה. terumah. He's just saying this isn't good
enough. Right? That's the language, אין זו חזקה ששורפין. ein zo chazakah
shesorfin. This is not a good enough and if you think about
it that's the case. It's not a case like people have been
living together for ten years and we presume this is the mother
and these are the father and these are the kids. It's not
like it's- not only is it not a good high enough the
same standard of proof, it's not the same qualitative reality. In one,
there was a presumption that got developed, a perception in society. Oh,
everybody knows now that she's a נידה. niddah. Everybody knows this is
a family, these are the parents and these are the kids. This
wasn't that case. There was no you know, just the kid touched
something and you wanted to know did he touch it or not.
It wasn't like this presumption that developed and
it's also like there's known that it's a question mark over it.
Did he touch it? I don't know. Did he not? Probably he
did. This is more like the question of did the person commit
murder? Right? Did this act take place? It's not the question of
a presumption of a status. It's a question of knowing whether the
act took place. So this is really a very, very different case.
It's not that by תרומה terumah we have a higher standard, it's
just that this scenario is a different scenario and therefore it's not
enough to burn תרומה terumah for it. Okay? And therefore the גמרא's
Gemara going to say there are scenarios that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
would burn תרומה terumah and that's the next question. אלא איזו חזקה
לרבי יוחנן ששורפין עליה את התרומה? Ela eizo chazakah l'Rabbi Yochanan shesorfin
aleha es haterumah? What would be a good enough חזקה chazakah for
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that you would burn תרומה? terumah? What would
be a scenario that would be qualitatively better? So כדתנן, kitna, like
we taught in the
משנה. Mishnah. עיסה בתוך הבית. Issah b'toch habayis. You got some dough
in the house. Or כדתניא, kitanya, שרצים וצפרדעים מטפלין שם. shratzim v'tzfardaim
mitaplim sham. And there are שרצים, shratzim, you know, impure rodents, that
if they were to touch the dough would make the dough impure.
And there are frogs which actually even are not impure. And they're
hopping around in the dough or in the house.
ונמצאו חתיכות בעיסה. V'nimtzu chatichot b'issah. And you find a little leg
of one animal in your dough. Okay. אם לאו, Im lav, is
it a frog leg? Okay and then it's a delicacy although it's
not kosher. But anyway, or is it a שרץ? shratz? So is
it a leg that makes the dough טמא tamei or not?
Okay. ונמצאו חתיכות בעיסה. V'nimtzu chatichot b'issah. אם רוב שרצים טמאה אם
רוב צפרדעים טהורה. Im rov shratzim tamei, im rov tzfardaim tehorah. And
there you would go by the majority. Okay, so there again that's
a little bit different. You know something touched, you don't know the
identity of the thing that touched, you're going to judge it based
on רוב. rov. Even that I think is not the same level
as the case of a family growing up in the community that
there develops a perception in the community that this is all a
family. Here there's no general perception that develops. Okay, but you're making
a decision based on רוב. rov. You know something touched, you have
to figure out what its identity is, you'll decide based on רוב.
rov. So bottom line is it is not that תרומה terumah has
a higher standard than executing people, okay? It's just that some cases
of תרומה terumah are more doubtful. You don't even know if the
kid touched the dough is different than when you know they touched
the dough and you're trying to figure out what exactly the identity
is. Different level- you're different scenarios, okay? They're not all the same
scenario. All right. So now
the
גמרא Gemara says
like
this. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן. Tanya k'vateh d'Rabbi Yochanan. We taught like
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. שני דברים אין בהם דעת לישאל. Shnei devarim
ein bahem da'as lishael.
There are two things that the person- the person there did not
have the ability to respond to questions. Because to say a ספק
ברשות היחיד safek b'reshus hayachid is טמא tamei is only if the
person who was present was able to respond to questions. We learned
that out from נידה. niddah. How do we know that a ספק
טומאה ברשות היחיד safek tumah b'reshus hayachid is טמא? tamei? A woman
goes in private with a man and we presume until we bring-
until we do the whole סוטה sotah ritual, but if there was
all the warning leading up to it, that they might have had
sex until we go ahead and, you know, can do the סוטה
sotah ritual to change that presumption. So therefore from that we apply
that somehow strangely to normal cases of ritual טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah
and say that if something is in a private space, a secluded
space and there's a question we presume it was טמא, tamei, but
only like the case of נידה niddah only if there was somebody
there that could have been asked about it.
Okay. The sages חכמים Chachamim made it
לישאל lisha'el as if the person could have been asked and therefore
we've ruled that it was טמא. tamei. תינוק, tinok, one was the
case of the infant. So by the way, you already see, technically
that infant should have been a case of ספק, safek, should have
been טהור, tahor, but we're going to treat it as if the
child could have been asked and therefore we're going to make it
טמא. tamei. That's why we're not going to burn the dough because
in principle that actually should have been טהור. tahor. ועוד אחרת ve'od
acheret and another one. תינוק הדאמרן tinok hada'amaran we said the case
of the infant. ועוד אחרת מאי ve'od acheret mai what's the other
one? עיסה בתוך הבית ותרנגולין ומשקין טמאים שם issah betoch habayit vetarnogolin
umashkin tmei'im sham there's dough in the house and there's chickens and
there is impure liquid, liquid that was טמא. tamei. Okay, some wine
that became טמא tamei or something. ונמצאו ניקורים ניקורים בעיסה venimtzu nikurim
nikurim be'issah and you see little peck holes in the dough. So
the question is, you know what happened with the dough, the chicken
was pecking away at it, but did the chicken have the טמא
tamei liquid in its mouth when it was pecking away at it
and therefore the טמא tamei liquid touched the dough? תולין לא אוכלין
ולא שורפין tolin lo ochlin velo sorfin again here you see like
Rabbi Yochanan, you're not going to burn the dough. אמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi okay, and even though they
are should have been a ספק safek and it should have been
טהור tahor because nobody could have been asked about it, we're going
to be מחמיר machmir and say טמא. tamei. So here are cases
where technically we should have said ספק טהור, safek tahor, we're going
to say טמא, tamei, we're not going to burn it, but it
doesn't mean that in תרומה terumah we'll never burn the dough based
on presumptions. It just means here the presumptions are not weighty enough
to burn the dough. אמר רבי יהושע amar Rabbi Yehoshua לא שנו
אלא במשקין לבנים lo shanu ella bemashkin levanim that's only by clear
liquids. אבל במשקין אדומים aval bemashkin adumim let's say they were red
liquids, it was wine, אם עיסה דנקר מידי ידיע im issah denakir
midei yadia if the chicken pecked away with it with some wine
in its beak then you would know, you would see little wine
drops in the dough. So if you don't see the wine drops,
you know that you're okay. So the גמרא Gemara says ודילמא באו
עיתין הוא עיסה vedilma ba'u itein hu issah maybe the wine touched
the dough and the chicken ate the dough that had the wine
drop on it, but the wine had first touched the dough and
made the dough טמא. tamei. You get the sequence? Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says
אמר רבי יוחנן דבר זה שמעתי מרבי ופירושו לא שמעתי. amar Rabbi
Yochanan davar zeh shama'ti me'Rabbi uperusho lo shamati. You know, this thing
I heard from the great one, meaning Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, but
I didn't hear the explanation, which is why it should matter what
color it is because why aren't we concerned that even if it's
like a red color, maybe the chicken ate the dough? But אמר
רבי יוחנן דבר זה שמע מרבי ופירושו לא שמעתי. amar Rabbi Yochanan
davar zeh shama me'Rabbi uperusho lo shamati. But לא שנו אלא במשקין
צלולים שבבבואה של תינוק ניכר בה lo shanu ella bemashkin tzelulim shebebabu'ah
shel tinok nikar bah אבל משקין עכורין לא. aval mashkin achurin lo.
This would only be if it was like a clear liquid that
the face of an infant could be seen in it, but if
it was somehow cloudy liquid, no. Now I'm not sure again, how
does that work? Oh, because רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi says if
it's not really one minute, yeah, רש"י Rashi says it's not really
about red versus white. It's that if it is red and clear,
meaning clear not transparent, but clear like no sediment or whatever, then
it could have been fully absorbed into the dough. But if it
was cloudy, then it would have stayed at the top of the
dough. I still don't really understand this because even if it weren't
to fully been absorbed in the dough, why don't we assume that
why aren't we still concerned that it touched the dough and that
the chicken ate it? So yeah, I don't really get that. Anyway,
the basic point is that if there's evidence that you might be
able to prove that it wasn't there if you would say that
had the chicken actually really had the liquid in its mouth, we
would have seen evidence of it remaining in the dough and since
we didn't, that could be proof that it did not eat it.
But bottom line is normal חזקה, chazakah, a presumption based on we
don't know for sure but it's just a perception and a presumption
that we have in society, that will establish things as facts that
then you could actually go out and execute somebody for. Okay, and
that's very different than but not all cases rise to that level.
Some of these תרומה terumah cases, it's not strong enough to lead
to a clear presumption of what those realities are and those would
be treated differently. Okay, very important in terms of those issues of
חזקה. chazakah. Yes, Charlie? One thing that they did not discuss in
terms of ראיה re'ayah or חזקה chazakah is פסול pasul of written
documentation. Well, no, that would be real proof. I mean, the question
would be what would constitute a legitimate שטר? shtar? Right now we
would say a birth certificate. Is a birth certificate a הלכה halakhic
שטר? shtar? So exactly right, what type of what what That is
a good point about things that the whole science of, I don't
have to tell you this, but what is it about, what is
it called forensic evidence, right, when it was first introduced everybody thought
it was a joke, right, obviously nothing means anything except an eyewitness.
You're going to go prove something based on a fingerprint or something?
Right? Right? So הלכה Halacha never got to the point where it
used non-direct testimony. And there's a good reason for that. I'm just
saying, so how would it deal with those realities nowadays? DNA evidence.
There is no הלכתי halachic basis for it, right? Could you say,
could you sort of work that into some existing concepts like a
חזקה, chazakah, presumption that if it is there, but right, I mean,
so that's important to know that,
but again, sometimes we use those evidence to presume who committed the
act, not just to presume certain facts, right? To use DNA evidence
or blood tests to determine who somebody's father is or whatever is
different than the evidence about committing the crime, which again, here we're
not, as I said before, evidence of committing the crime always had
to be direct testimony. This is about establishing facts and evidence ahead
of time. Okay,
let's take a look. Now we switch, a significant switching of gears,
yes. There
was research about the unreliability of eyewitness testimony. Exactly. That is the
whole problem, that eyewitness testimony is, I mean, that is the irony,
right, that we did not accept traditionally forensic evidence and now we
know that it is actually much better, much more reliable. I mean,
obviously there's always presumptions and things, other possible interpretations, but right, exactly.
All right, now we really get to the final משניות mishnayot in
קידושין, Kiddushin, which is a significant break from some of the earlier
discussions, which has to do with the laws of ייחוד, yichud, about
a man and woman being in seclusion, and a concern they're not
allowed to be because they might have sex, and the interesting thing
is you could have sort of connected it somehow to issues about
ייחוס yichus or whatever, maybe if she's a wife of a כהן
kohen or who knows what the case might be, but that's not
the concern. The concern goes back to the more normal concerns of
מסכת קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, which
interestingly, the general point by the way of
question about sex outside of marriage never really got addressed. I know
some people are aware it is actually מחלוקת ראשונים machloket Rishonim because
the תורה Torah has these whole cases of a פילגש, pilegesh, of
concubines, which now there is a question about how institutionalized was concubinage,
how much did it require some act of maybe קידושין kiddushin without
a כתובה, kesuvah, some formal act in order to make it whatever.
But רמב"ם Rambam basically says sex outside of marriage is forbidden,
whereas רמב"ן Ramban says that it's actually
monogamous and type of committed and monogamous, it is actually not forbidden
assuming the woman isn't a נדה. niddah. So you could imagine that
the ייחוד yichud would be a concern about that, but actually as
we will see, the primary concerns about ייחוד yichud are concerns about
when the woman is not just single, but like she's forbidden for
more weighty reasons. She's a married woman, or she's a relative, which
is interesting. What, you can't, brother and sister can't be together? How
does it really apply to relatives? I mean, mother and son obviously
can be together, so there is a whole question about whether it
applies to siblings or not. Okay, but let's say she's a married
woman would be one case. It doesn't apply to a man whose
woman is a נדה. niddah. They're allowed, right, husband and wife can
share a bedroom together if the woman's a נדה. niddah. So basically,
but it would apply to an
unmarried woman who's a נדה. niddah. So the basic classic cases of
ייחוד yichud really are like a single woman who's a נדה niddah
and a married woman. Now in the time of the גמרא, Gemara,
single women nowadays, women before they get married don't go to the
מקווה. mikvah. So basically, the laws of ייחוד yichud would naturally apply
to men and single women because single women would be a נדה.
niddah. But in the time of the גמרא, Gemara, single women would
go to the מקווה mikvah if they wanted to handle תרומה, terumah,
other types of things, just for טומאה tumah טהרה tahara everybody would
go to the מקווה mikvah for any reason that they were טמא.
tamei. So actually the גמרא Gemara sort of says that the איסור
issur of ייחוד yichud with a single woman who's not a נדה
niddah was actually a much later תקנה. takanah. But the prime איסור
issur of ייחוד yichud was really with married woman and a woman
who was not a man's wife who was a נדה. niddah. Anyway,
so that's interesting that again, I mean I don't know where else
it would get discussed, but what exactly is it doing in מסכת
קידושין? Masechet Kiddushin? Maybe again because it's about another man's wife. Okay,
but anyway that is what the end of the מסכת masechet focuses
on is about cases of ייחוד. yichud. So let's take a look
at the משנה. mishna.
לא יתייחד אדם עם שתי נשים. Lo yityached adam im shtei nashim.
A man should not be in seclusion
with two
women. אבל אשה אחת מתייחדת עם שני אנשים, Aval isha achas mityachedes
im shnei anashim, but one woman can be in seclusion with two
men. That's strange. What's the difference? Presumably if there's a third party,
let the third party be the chaperone. What difference does it make
if the third party is a woman or the third party is
a man? רבי שמעון אומר אף
איש אחד מתייחד עם שתי נשים. Rabbi Shimon omer af ish echad
mityached im shtei nashim. So that's what Rabbi Shimon says. Yes, as
long as there's three people, we're not afraid that two of them
are going to go off and have sex. Okay, now here's a
very big question here about how to read this next line, whether
this is a continuation of Rabbi Shimon or it's a separate line.
I'm going to read it like תוספות Tosafot because it'll just keep
things clearer and it's more consistent with the way we פוסקן. pasken.
So תוספות Tosafot adds a ו vav
here. ובזמן שאשתו עמו. U'vizman she'ishto imo. Now, not relating to Rabbi
Shimon's position. First there was the position is a third
person, is a third party, a second woman enough to remove יחוד?
yichud? Now here's another thing that will remove יחוד. yichud. If a
man is with his wife, ישן עמהם בפונדקי. yashen imahem be'pundeki. Takes
out the ו vav after moves the ו. vav. ובזמן שאשתו עמו
ישן עמהם בפונדקי מפני שאשתו משמרתו. U'vizman she'ishto imo yashen imahem be'pundeki
mipnei she'ishto meshamarto. If a man is with two women but one
of them is his wife, okay, then he can or three women
and one of them is his wife, whatever, but even even two
women, then he can go ahead and they can all be share,
you know, sleeping together in an inn because we assume that his
wife will keep an eye on him. All right, so one exception
to the laws of יחוד yichud is that a man is with
his wife. Now,
מתייחד
אדם עם אמו ועם בתו. mityached adam im imo ve'im bito. A
man can be together with his mother or his daughter. Notice it's
all from the male perspective, his wife, that's why it's his mother
or daughter. וישן עמהם בקירוב בשר veyashen imahem be'keiruv basar and can
even sleep together with them, you know, with, you know, flesh to
flesh. ואם הגדילו ve'im higdilu but that's only when the when the
children are when like he as a boy is still a small
boy he can sleep with his mother or when his daughter is
small. Once the child becomes an adult, what exactly an adult is,
זו ישנה בכסותה וזה ישן בכסותו. zo yeshena bi'kesutah ve'zeh yashen bi'kesuto.
They can share a bed but they have to be in some
type of clothing. They have to be in night clothes. They can't
actually be without naked together in bed. You know, which is on
the one hand, obviously, you know, you have to, first of all,
they didn't have a lot of beds in those days, they had
to share beds, right? And you know, and obviously you're not going
to אסר assur יחוד yichud between a father and a child. On
the other hand, like, you know, there's something a little disturbing because
we are aware about cases of incest, right? But but you know,
but on the other hand, what are you going to say? You
know, father can't be alone with his daughter? Right, so I mean,
you know, so you do understand these rulings. Actually it becomes very,
very challenging is dealing with the הלכות halachot of יחוד yichud and
נגיעה negiya in cases of adopted children. You know, there's some פוסקים,
poskim, I don't understand how they think these kids are supposed to
grow up normally, that say that you can't have יחוד yichud or
you can't, you know, you can't be affectionate with your adopted children
of the other sex. Right? I mean, ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, there
are פוסקים poskim פוסקן pasken otherwise. But what? Because they're like any
other person that you're not related to. You know, so they don't
have the status of a child. Right? So they obviously, you know,
anyway, there's like, you did something, didn't you something about somebody else,
were we discussing it though when we did... Yeah, okay. Anyway, but
I can give you some sources on that. Anyway, but so what
we have here though is these laws of יחוד. yichud. I should
say two other things just which don't come up directly in the
גמרא Gemara but I should just mention at the outset about יחוד.
yichud. One is, is the concern of יחוד, yichud, I'll say three
things here, is the concern of יחוד yichud number one of consensual
sex... Excuse me, of rape or even of consensual sex? Okay? Generally
the presumption is is that it's a concern of both. Okay? But
the פוסקים poskim deal with certain types of scenarios. Maybe you don't
have to be concerned about one, but you're concerned about another, like
some cases about what what do you do if there's like very
strict, you know,
secular law around rape or whatever. Everyone knows it doesn't doesn't mean
that people don't get away with it anyway, but you know, but
would that address some of these יחוד yichud concerns? And the basic
consensus of the פוסקים poskim is that these are concerns not about
just limited to rape, but they also include concerns about consensual sex,
which seems clear from all the גמרות. Gemarot. There's no distinction about
those. The other related issue, which I find fascinating, is are these...
everything here is said from the male perspective, like most of הלכה
halacha is said from the male perspective, but is the concern just
about the man or is it even a concern about the woman?
Is it a concern that the man might go ahead and initiate
sex with the woman or would it even be in the reverse?
Now you might say what difference does it make, right? As long
as they can't be private together, who cares who we're concerned about?
One scenario that comes up in the פוסקים poskim is
let's say they're staying in a, you know, in a
shared apartment, or let's say I don't know in an office building,
and there's a locked door between them, okay, but but the question
is will that help? So how could... why would it help? Somebody
can always open up the door, right? That's the question. Who cares
if the door's locked? Presumably it's not if a third party has
the key, presumably if I'm behind a locked door, I can always
Somebody can always open up the door, right? That's the question. Who
cares if the door's locked? Presumably it's not a third party has
the key. Presumably if I'm behind a locked door, I can open
up the locked door, right? So some say, ah, but if it
is the woman behind the locked door and the man doesn't have
the key, then it's okay, because we're not concerned that the woman
is going to initiate the ייחוד. yichud. We're only concerned that the
man is going to initiate, right? So you get that scenario. So
if the woman is behind the locked door, there's no way the
man can initiate the situation. The ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer disagrees. He
says, I have searched low and high and I cannot find any
evidence that this is only concern about the man and not a
concern about the woman. Like any other area of הלכה, halacha, we
should presume it applies equally to men and to women, although he
actually is lenient about the locked door regardless of whose door is
locked because he just thinks they're fundamentally in separate rooms, it really
doesn't matter. But he says as a principle, right, that's the question:
are we just concerned about the man as the initiator or are
we even concerned potentially as the woman is the initiator? The third
issue I want to just raise as a conceptual issue to put
on the table is the question of,
and this gets to the locked door case, is it that ייחוד
yichud to prevent to say it's not ייחוד, yichud, it has to
be that it's not possible for them to have sex if they
don't want to, even if they would want to? Or do we
have to just say they're not in a situation, the concern isn't
that they're going to want to
have sex consciously, because then nobody's going to if they're not going
to follow הלכות ייחוד? hilchos yichud? If you're trying to do something,
who's paying attention to הלכות ייחוד hilchos yichud anyway? The concern is,
the concern is that you're not going to be able to resist
temptation. And therefore the primary goal of this is to avoid situations
of temptation. So the נפקא מינא nafka mina would be exactly this
case of a door between them. A lot of פוסקים poskim would
say, the door between them, big deal, they could just open up
the door, nothing is stopping them from having sex. Whereas the ציץ
אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer says, we're not presuming that they're starting by planning
on having sex, we're starting by assuming that they might be tempted.
If they're in different rooms with a door between them and they
remain in different rooms, because they're not in a situation where they're
being tempted, the fact that they could open up the door makes
it, that's a different story. Okay, so it's a very interesting question
about whether we have to make it not possible or just make
it a situation in which they're not, they're reasonably not going to
be tempted. Alright, anyway, so those are some of the issues around
ייחוד. yichud. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So the
first thing the גמרא Gemara wants to know is the position of
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that two men with one woman is
okay but not the reverse. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? תנא דבי אליהו,
Tana devei Eliyahu, ותנא דבי אליהו, v'tana devei Eliyahu, הואיל ונשים דעתן
קלות עליהן. Hocheil venashim da'atan kalos aleihen.
Since women were easy to be seduced, which therefore means that one
man with two women, he might be able to seduce both of
them, he might be able to seduce one and have the other
one not object. But here's some sense that men are more in
control of their passions,
or I don't know, a better moral fiber, whatever the presumption is,
but sounds like they're also just of more strong-willed, and therefore if
it's two men, the guy who's not party to it is going
to be the is going to object and is going to prevent
it and is going to sort of. But if it's two women,
you're more be able to get away with it. That's the presumption
the גמרא Gemara makes, which isn't the same as the question of
who is the initiator, it's just a, but it's, I mean, it's
related but it's not the same. That's why the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma assumes that one man with two women is no good. The
question then becomes what about one man with three women, right? What
would according to that, would you never get out of ייחוד yichud
until you had two men according to that, or could there be
enough women that it would not be a problem? That's discussed in
the פוסקים. poskim. Okay, מנא הני מילי? minani mili? Where do you
get this whole idea of ייחוד? yichud? אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי
ישמעאל, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yishmael, רמז לייחוד מן התורה מנין?
Remez leyichud min hatorah minayin? Where do you know it from? שנאמר,
Shene'emar, כי יסיתך אחיך בן אמך, ki yesit-cha achicha ben imcha, then
your brother, your mother's son seduces you, and this is about talking
about עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. וכי בן אם מסית בן אב אין
מסית? Vechi ben em masis, ben av ein masis? Why does it
say your mother's son? Would only your mother's son try to seduce
you to עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, not your father's son? אלא לומר
לך בן מתייחד עם אמו, Ela lomar lach ben mityached im imo,
to tell you there's an idea of בן אם, ben em, the
son of a mother, that the son can be in seclusion with
his mother. בן אם מתייחד עם אמו ואסור להתייחד עם כל עריות
שבתורה. Ben im mityached im imo, ve'asur lehityached im kol arayos shebatorah.
And other forbidden עריות, arayos,
you can't be in ייחוד yichud together with. So we learn out
the איסור ייחוד issur yichud from the fact that a brother is
described as your mother's son. And that teaches you that the only
secluded scenario the Torah allows for is a son and his mother,
but not other other relatives, which by the way makes it sound
like siblings would be not acceptable, which is a whole discussion in
the פוסקים. poskim. Anyway, this sounds quite far-fetched, okay, and therefore I
think most of us would reasonably assume this is an אסמכתא. asmachta.
But based on other גמרות, Gemaras, another גמרא Gemara says ייחוד דאורייתא
היא, yichud d'oraisa hi, which again, some פוסקים poskim read to mean
it's a רמז remez in the Torah, it's an אסמכתא, asmachta, but
overwhelmingly, most פוסקים poskim presume that this is really seen as a
תורה דין, Torah din, ייחוד. yichud. The one case that's seen as
Rabbinic is the case I told you before, ייחוד עם פנויה, yichud
im penuyah, ייחוד, yichud, a man and a single
woman. Right. So you're saying but that would be evidence that it's
דאורייתא d'oraisa or not. The fact that he calls it a רמז.
remez. Right, I agree. The fact that he calls it a רמז,
remez, the fact that there's a pretty far-fetched read of the פסוק,
pasuk, you know, but it is interesting as far as what halachic
weight is given. Let's read one more line. פשטיה דקרא במאי כתיב.
Peshatia d'kra b'mai ksiv.
Okay, that's the דרשה, drasha, that's the רמז. remez. But what's the
simple sense of the פסוק? pasuk? Why does it speak about being
seduced by your mother's brother to commit עבודה זרה avoda zara and
not by your father's brother? I mean, your mother's son and not
your father's son. So אמר אביי לא מיבעיא קאמר. Amar Abaye lo
mibaya ka'amar. The פסוק pasuk is telling you goes without saying.
לא מיבעיא בן אב דסני ליה ואית ליה עיצה רעה, Lo mibaya
ben av d'sani lei v'ais lei eitza ra'ah, but the Torah is
saying don't listen to your brother who's trying to seduce you to
do עבודה זרה. avoda zara. It wouldn't have to tell you that
if it was your brother on your father's side. You'd be more
inclined not to listen to him because you know your brother on
your father's side is competing with you for your father's inheritance. So
he might be trying to get you killed, right, get you to
worship עבודה זרה, avoda zara, get you out of the picture. So
it goes without saying don't listen to your brother on your father's
side. אלא אפילו בן אם, Ela afilu ben em, even your brother
on your mother's side that's not competing with you for your father's
inheritance, דלא סני ליה, d'lo sani lei, and you can't assume that
he hates you, אימא ציית ליה, eima tzeis lei, you might think
oh, he's got a good idea, let's go be עובד עבודה זרה,
oved avoda zara, maybe I should listen to it. קא משמע לן
Ka mashma lan that you should not listen to him. Okay, so
anyway we will pick up with this tomorrow in terms of the
parameters of יחוד yichud of one man and two women as opposed
to one woman and two men.